Guide to the Carlisle Indian: The Newsletter of the Carlisle Club BCMS.0024
Brooklyn Collection
Carlisle Indian: The Newsletter of the Carlisle Club
1939-1944
Brooklyn Collection
Drapkin, Eli, 1918-2006
BCMS.0024
0.4 Linear feet in 1 legal-sized document box
38 issues of The Carlisle Indian, a newsletter for members of the Carlisle Club, dating from 1939-1944. The Carlisle Club of East Flatbush, Brooklyn was a Jewish youth organization founded in 1931.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit. This collection contains fragile material which cannot be photocopied.
Provenance
Purchased in two parts from two different sources in 2018. Support for this collection has been provided by The David Berg Foundation.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes 69 copies of 38 issues of the Carlisle Indian newsletter, published for and by members of the Carlisle Club. The issues in this collection date from October 1939 to November 1944. Some copies are typewritten and some are mimeographed. All are on 8.5x14" sheets of paper. Eighteen issues have photographic prints attached to their front pages; Vol. XII, No. 12 features three different images across its four copies.
Historical Note
The Carlisle Club was founded in 1931 in East Flatbush, Brooklyn. The club promoted social and athletic activities in the area but also aimed to educate its members and raise their cultural awareness. As part of this, the group promoted anti-war beliefs and held peace rallies, until the attack on Pearl Harbor resulted in many of the club's members joining the war effort.
The Carlisle Indian is the Club's newsletter, edited by member Eli Drapkin (1918-2006) while he was stationed at Camp Shelby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi. Later issues were edited by Eli's wife Ruth. Some of the copies in this collection may have been owned by the Drapkins, since they include a mock-up of one issue, duplicate copies of several issues, and copies with handwritten corrections.
The newsletter is organized into several recurring columns and also includes information on Carlisle Club activities. The column "Letter of the Month" began in early 1943 and includes highly descriptive correspondence from club members serving overseas.
Arrangement
The 38 issues of the newsletter in this collection are arranged in publication order. They are listed below by volume, number, and date.
Related Materials
Merlis, Brian. Brooklyn's East Flatbush. Brooklyn, NY: brooklynpix.com in conjunction with Israelowitz Publishing, 2009.
Flatbush Times newspaper (1952-1959) in the Local Newspapers on Microfilm collection.
Brooklyn Collection clipping files on East Flatbush.
Brooklyn Newsstand for World War II coverage in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle.
East Flatbush; Newsletters; World War, 1939-1945; The Carlisle Club of East Flatbush.
- Volume IX
  - No. 2, October 14, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - No. 4, December 23, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - No. 5, January 29, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - No. 6, March 2, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - No. 7, April 6, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Volume X
  - No. 1, May 17, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - No. 2, July 19, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - No. 3, October 1, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - No. 4, December 1, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Volume XII
  - Preview Edition, June 21, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - No. 1, July 19, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Note
    2 copies.
  - No. 2, August 22, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - No. 3, October 4, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - No. 4, October 18, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes photograph.
  - No. 5, November 8, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - No. 6, November 22, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - No. 7, December 13, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    4 copies.
  - No. 8, January 17, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    4 copies, 2 of which include photographs.
  - No. 9, February 7, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    2 copies, one of which includes a photograph.
  - No. 10, February 28, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - No. 11, March 21, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    3 copies.
  - No. 12, April 17, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    4 copies, all four of which include photographs.
- Volume XIII
  - No. 1, May 10, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - No. 2, June 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - No. 3, July 25, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    3 copies, two that include photographs.
  - No. 4, August 30, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - No. 4 [5], September 30, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - No. 6, October 31, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    2 copies, both of which include photographs.
  - No. 7, November 30, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - No. 8, December 31, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    3 copies, all of which include photographs.
  - No. 9, January 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - No. 10, February 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - No. 12, April 30, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Volume XIV
  - No. 1, May 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - No. 3, July 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - No. 4, August 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - No. 5, September 30, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - No. 6, November 4, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)